Samuel Hooper Collection
Samuel Hooper Collection
1856-1874
Hooper, Samuel, 1808-1875.
21 items (SC)
Papers of the American merchant, legislator from Massachusetts. Twenty items of outgoing correspondence about politics (Schuyler Colfax), interpretation of the usury law (Nahum Capen), as well as social invitations (Adam Badeau, Benjamin Perley Poore) and a letter of introduction (Charles Sumner).
149377
Biographical History
Samuel Hooper (1808-1875) was an American politician who served as a U.S. Representative from 1861-1875.
Samuel Hooper was born in Marblehead, Massachusetts on February 3, 1808. In 1832 Hooper married Anne Sturgis whose father owned a shipping firm. Hooper worked at his father-in-law's firm as a junior partner, gradually expanding his interests, eventually shifting into the iron business. In 1850, he was elected to the State House of Representatives. Hooper served as a representative from 1851-1853. He attended the Republican National Convention in 1860 as a delegate from Massachusetts. Hooper was elected to fill the vacancy left by William Appleton in the U.S. House of Representatives in 1861 and continued to hold a position in Congress from 1861 to 1875. While in Congress, Hooper was a chairman of the Committee on Ways and Means, and served on the Committee on Banking and Currency and the Committee on Coinage, Weights, and Measures at various points. Hooper's daughter, Alice Mason Hooper, married Charles Sumner in 1866, making Hooper Sumner's father-in-law; however, the marriage was short-lived. Hooper died on February 14, 1875 while still in office.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Samuel Hooper Collection is a group of 20 items of Outgoing Correspondence written between 1856 and 1874, and a single Miscellaneous item, all of which relate to the U.S. congressional representative and senator from Massachusetts.
The Correspondence includes discussions about politics (Schuyler Colfax) and the interpretation of the usury laws (Nahum Capen) as well as social invitations (Mr. Anthony Adam Badeau, Benjamin Perley Poore) and a letter of introduction (Charles Sumner). The correspondence includes a series of three letters written in October of 1865 to Schuyler Colfax about Nathaniel Prentiss Banks who, upon returning from military duty after the Civil War, was nominated to run for the House of Representatives from Massachusetts (12 Oct 1865):
Talking with Sumner about Banks's nomination, last evening, Sumner said it was the greatest personal triumph a man ever had in Massts. - to come back here as he did into a district that seemed to be already disposed of - and in two weeks to be taken up and nominated over all the competitors.
Reassuring Colfax that the remarkable Banks had no intention of challenging the incumbent for leadership of the House, Hooper writes (13 Oct 1865):
...he will not be a candidate for the Speakership, and as I have said before, I am sure he will not be in your way, but on the contrary will cordially cooperate with your friends to secure your election.
The Miscellaneous series contains a printed letter from Benjamin Perley Poore, in his capacity as Clerk of Printing Records, to which is affixed a proof of the Hooper entry (with holograph additions) for inclusion in the Congressional Directory.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection contains two series: Correspondence, which is arranged chronologically, and Miscellany. An alphabetical Index to the Correspondence is located at the end of the finding aid.
Subject and Genre Headings
Politics, government and public administration; Badeau, Adam, 1831-1895.; Banks, Nathaniel Prentiss, 1816-1894.; Capen, Nahum,1904-1886.; Colfax, Schuyler, 1823-1885.; Hooper, Samuel, 1808-1875.; Poore, Benjamin Perley, 1820-1887.; Sumner, Charles, 1811-1874.; Republican Party (Mass.); Legislators -- United States.; Politicians -- United States.; Usury laws -- United States.; Massachusetts -- Politics and government -- 1865-1950.; United States -- Politics and government -- 1865-1877.; Letters (correspondence); Legislators.; Politicians.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Inventory
- Correspondence
  - Outgoing Correspondence
    - [General], 1856-1861; 3 items (Sc 102)
    - [General], 1865; 3 items (Sc 102)
    - [General], 1867-1868; 3 items (Sc 102)
    - [General], 1869-1870; 3 items (Sc 102)
    - [General], 1872-1874; 2 items (Sc 102)
    - [General], undated; 6 items (Sc 102)
- Miscellaneous
  - Congressional Directory, 1867; proof for Samuel Hooper entry with his corrections (Sc 102)
Selected index to correspondence
Anthony, Mr. undated
Badeau, Adam 14 Jun 1868 26 Feb 1869 18 Apr 1869 05 Mar 1870 undated (2 items)
Capen, Nahum 02 Mar 1856 05 Jun 1857
Colfax, Schuyler 12 Oct 1865 (2 items) 13 Oct 1865
Poore, Benjamin Perley 22 Dec 1867 24 Jul 1874
Stockwell, Stephen N. 04 Dec 1861
Sumner, Charles 23 May 1872 undated (2 items)
Wakeman, Maurice 28 Apr 1867
Wightman, Mayor undated